A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Education and Culture, Office Files of Peter W. Stanley FA603
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Education and Culture, Office Files of Peter W. Stanley
1980-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stanley, Paul W.
Ford Foundation
FA603
11.02 Cubic Feet 29 LTR size Hollinger boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
A later set of Peter W. Stanley Office Files was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:030. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in May 2019.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Peter W. Stanley who served as Program Officer in Charge and then Program Director of the Ford Foundation's Education and Culture Program from between 1983 and 1991. The Education and Culture Program was situated within the Foundation's United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP). In addition to holding the records that Stanley and his office created and maintained, the collection also includes some material from the larger Education and Culture Program. A few of these documents were created from before and after Stanley's tenure at the Foundation. The records' creators appear to have organized Stanley's files according to file type. The collection's arrangement scheme represents these different types with the implementation of 4 different series. The series are: Series 1. Correspondence files; Series 2. Subject files; Series 3. Meeting and trip files; and Series 4. General files. However, terms like Desk file and Work file were also used to label many of the collection's files and remain part of those files' titles. Moreover, there does not appear to be a clear distinction between the structure and content of files in Series 4. General files and some of the files in Series 1. Correspondence files. Different and evolving filing systems were probably imposed on the records throughout their creation, use, and management.
Correspondence, memoranda, program reviews, budgets, notes, drafts, and reports document the Education and Culture Program's grant giving priorities and activities during this time period. Two major areas of concern were the improvement of access and equity in higher education through increased recruitment and retention of minority students and the improvement of undergraduate education through enhanced teaching, scholarship, and academic programs. Materials in the collection also regard the Education and Culture Program's interest in assessing the need for special support to the Philippines following the presidency of Ferdinand Marcos, cultural preservation, and the Ford Foundation's developing External Affirmative Action Program (EAAP).
Other material types found within the collection include brochures, invitations, schedules, invoices, participant lists, publications, Recommended Grant Action reports (RGAs), and press releases.
The collection consists of more than one accession of Peter W. Stanley office files. A later set of records transferred to and ingested by the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2019 (Accession 2019:030) shared the same file types as the original material and was therefore integrated into the established collection. These later files were added to the appropriate series and placed where the original files ended.
Arrangement
Arranged in 4 series by file type. Material originating from the first accession of Peter W. Stanley Office Files remains at the beginning of each series. The material from the later set of records (Accession 2019:030) shared the same file types as the records in the original accession. Therefore, it was divided across the 4 different series during processing and added to where the first files ended.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological files, 1983-1992
Series 2. Subject files, 1980-1991
Series 3. Meeting and trip files, 1980-1991
Series 4. General files, 1986-1992
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
Peter W. Stanley has worked as an educator and foundation program officer. He served in the Ford Foundation's Education and Culture Program from between 1983 and 1991. His initial position was Program Officer in Charge, and then in 1988, he became Program Director.
Stanley earned his undergraduate and graduate degrees from Harvard University. Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Stanley taught American and American-East Asian History at Harvard and the University of Illinois. He later served as Dean of the College at Carleton College.
After leaving the Ford Foundation, Stanley became President of Pomona College. He retired from that position in 2003.
Ford Foundation; Education, Higher; Affirmative action programs; Educational equalization; Multiculturalism; Philippines; Universities and colleges -- Faculty
- Correspondence files, 1983-1992; 1; 5.13 Cubic Feet About 13.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the correspondence files of Peter W. Stanley and the larger Ford Foundation Education and Culture Program from between 1983 and 1992. Not all of the correspondence files in the series are organized in the same way. Files titled Chronological correspondence contain correspondence from a particular segment of time (such as a year), alphabetically arranged by the name of the correspondent. There are also some files that contain subsections that group together different pieces of correspondence based upon the entity (or entities) that was principally responsible for creating those items. Miscellaneous correspondence files mostly contain invitations to events from external organizations and individuals.
  The correspondence in the series mainly regards requests for grant funding, grant supported projects, program administration, and program reviews.
  - Chronological correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Correspondence - Africa and Middle East Programs (John Gerhart), 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - Asia Programs (Peter Geithner), 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - Consultants, 1983-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence - Berresford/Gaberman/Jaffe, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - Education and Culture Director, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
    File subheadings include:
    Peter Stanley
    Edgar Beckham
    Sheila Biddle
    Barbara Hatton
    Ruth Mayleas
    Steven Zwerling
  - Correspondence - Interoffice, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Interoffice (other programs), 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - Latin America and the Caribbean Programs (Thomas Trebat), 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - Office of Communications (Andrea Taylor), 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    File only contains a cross reference notice.
  - Correspondence - President/Chairman (Franklin A. Thomas and Edson W. Spencer), 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - General information, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Budget
  - Trustees - Current information, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - United States International Affairs Program (USIAP) administration (Michele Cole and Roberta Lynch), 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Education and Culture chronological correspondence, 1990 June-August (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
    Files subheadings include:
    Hatton, Barbara
    Nelson, Barbara
    Cole, Michele
    Biddle, Sheila
    Stanley, Peter
    Mayleas, Ruth
    Beckham, Edgar
  - Education and Culture chronological correspondence, 1989 August-October (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
    Berresford, Susan
    Meade, Edward Jr.
    Boyer, Ernest
  - Education and Culture chronological correspondence, 1989 October-November (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
    Bernstein, Allison
  - Chronological correspondence - Correspondents A-D, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 31-32)
  - Chronological correspondence - Correspondents, E-L, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 33-34)
  - Chronological correspondence - Correspondents, M-Z, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 37-40)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 41-44)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 45-46)
  - Chronological correspondence, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 47-50)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 51-52)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 53-54)
  - Correspondence - William D. Carmichael, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence - Prue Brown, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence - Office of Reports, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Interoffice correspondence - Program Officers in Charge and program staff, 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    Bernstein, Alison
    McCarthy, Nancy
  - Correspondence - John D. Gerhart (Developing Countries Program), 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Interoffice correspondence (other programs), 1986 (Box 9, Folder 60-62)
    Administrative Services
    Archives
    Developing Countries Program - Peter Geithner, et al
    Human Rights
    International Affairs
    Program Related Investments (PRI)
    Secretary's Office
    Urban Poverty
  - Interoffice correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence - Franklin A. Thomas, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence - Susan V. Berresford, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Education and Culture staff correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 10, Folder 66-68)
    Allison Bernstein
    Linn Cary
    Nancy McCarthy
  - Correspondence - Susan V. Berresford, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 69-70)
  - Interoffice correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 71-73)
    Comptroller
    Developing Countries Program – Peter Geithner, et al.
    Personnel
    Rural Poverty
  - Correspondence - Office of Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 74-76)
  - Correspondence - William D. Carmichael, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - Correspondence - Franklin A. Thomas, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 78)
  - Correspondence - Developing Countries Program (DCP), 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence - Berresford/Gaberman/Jaffe, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence - President/Chairman (Franklin A. Thomas and Edson W. Spencer), 1990 (Box 12, Folder 81)
  - Correspondence - Education and Culture Director, 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 82-83)
    Alison Bernstein
    Barbara Nelson
  - Trustees - Current information, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence - Africa and Middle East Programs (John Gerhart), 1989-1990 (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence - Office of Communications, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Interoffice correspondence, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Correspondence - Latin America and the Caribbean Programs (Thomas Trebat), 1990 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Interoffice correspondence (other programs), 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 89-92)
    Human Rights and Governance
    Rural Poverty and Resources
  - Interoffice correspondence (other programs), 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 93-94)
    Developing Countries Program
  - Correspondence - Office of Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - Education and Culture staff correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 96-97)
  - Correspondence - Barry D. Gaberman/Susan V. Berresford, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 98)
  - Correspondence - Franklin A. Thomas, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Desk file - Developing Countries Program (DCP), 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 100)
    Brazil (Rio)
    Bangladesh (Dhaka)
    China (Beijing)
    Lima
    Nairobi
    New Delhi (India, Nepal, Sri Lanka)
    Mexico City
    Indonesia
- Subject files, 1980-1991; 2; 2.76 Cubic Feet About 7.25 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Series consists of the subject files that Peter W. Stanley and the larger Ford Foundation Education and Culture Program created from between 1980 and 1991. Files regard internal Education and Culture concerns like program reviews, program budgets, and the External Affirmative Action Program (EAAP) as well as higher education and other education and cultural-related projects and initiatives the Program supported. Many of those projects focused on improving access and equity in higher education through the increased recruitment and retention of minority students and improving undergraduate education through enhanced teaching, scholarship, and academic programs.
  - Desk file - Burton Clark, University of California Los Angeles, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Desk file - Corporations and Foundations Common Interest Group, 1988-1991 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Desk file - Directors' lunch, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Desk file - United States International Affairs Program (USIAP) Media Initiative, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Desk file - United States International Affairs Program (USIAP) program reviews, 1985-1987 (Box 15, Folder 105-107)
  - Donors to African Education (DAE), 1989-1991 (Box 15, Folder 108-110)
  - Minorities in Academic Careers - The Experience of Ford Foundation Fellows, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 111-112)
  - Minority Teacher Education and Rural Education grants (Barbara Hatton), 1988 (Box 16, Folder 113)
  - Desk file - RFP (request for proposal) model, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 114)
  - Undergraduate Education Initiative, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 115)
  - Women's Program Forum, 1985-1988 (Box 16, Folder 116-117)
  - Work file - Tomas Rivera Center, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 118)
  - Work file - Tulane University, 1990-1991 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Work file - World Music Institute, Inc., 1987-1988 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - Alsie Falconer - Campus Diversity Initiative work file, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 121-123)
  - Miscellaneous items - John Badgley, 1989-1990 (Box 17, Folder 124)
    American Association for the Advancement of Sciences (AAAS) memo regarding librarians conference
    American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) trip notes
    Southeast Asia Libraries
  - Miscellaneous items - National Foreign Language Center (NFLC), 1986-1989 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - Miscellaneous items - National Foreign Language Center (NFLC), 1989 (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - Miscellaneous items - Nancy Wilson/Mary Zurbuchen, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - National Foreign Language Center (NFLC) - Craufurd Goodwin Report, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 128)
  - Undergraduate Education Initiative - Work file, 1985-1988 (Box 18, Folder 129-131)
    11/85 Report - David Davis-Van Atta
    12/85 Trustees docket item
    Invitation letters (41 universities/colleges)
    6/86 Updated lists (41 universities/colleges)
    Ford Foundation Letter
    Consultants
    12/85 Press release
    Miscellaneous correspondence
    RGAs for 31 grants
  - Undergraduate Education Initiative, 1987-1989 (Box 18, Folder 132-135)
    Invitation letters
    Acceptances
    Second letter with attachments
    Preliminary agenda
    Comments from participants
    New York Public Library (NYPL) contract
    List of participants
    Papers for workshop
  - Undergraduate Education Initiative Meeting, 1989-1991 (Box 19, Folder 136)
  - Race relations, 1988-1990 (Box 19, Folder 137)
  - Urban Community College Transfer Opportunities Program (UCCTOP), 1983-1984 (Box 19, Folder 138-141)
    UCCTOP – Second stage, 7/84
    Academy for Educational Development (AED) site visits, March/April/1984
    1st follow-up meeting – 1984
    Press release
    Delegated Authority Project (DAP) #839-0495
    Rejection letters
    National Selection Panel
    Application form
    Announcement letter
    Miscellaneous internal
    Miscellaneous external
  - Memoranda - Estela Bensimon on Urban Community College Transfer Opportunities Program (UCCTOP), 1983 (Box 19, Folder 142)
  - Correspondence - Estela Bensimon on Urban Community College Transfer Opportunities Program (UCCTOP), 1983 (Box 19, Folder 143)
  - Race Relations and Campus Diversity Initiative, 1989-1990 (Box 20, Folder 144-145)
  - Special projects/Assignments, 1983-1986 (Box 20, Folder 146)
    Highlights - Trustees Docket
    Discussion - Developing Countries Program Meeting 10/84
    Miscellaneous
  - Special projects, 1986-1987 (Box 20, Folder 147)
    Grantmaking Seminars (Alison Bernstein/Ruth Mayleas)
    National Service Task Force
    Pluralism Review
  - General information, 1985-1986 (Box 20, Folder 148)
    Budget information
    Education and Culture Codes
    Staff assignments
  - Budgets, 1986-1987 (Box 20, Folder 149)
  - Budgets, 1988-1989 (Box 20, Folder 150)
  - General information, 1990 (Box 20, Folder 151)
  - Desk file - Artists' retirement/medical/survivors benefits, 1984 September 25 (Box 20, Folder 152)
  - Endowed Chairs supported by Ford Foundation, 1981 December (Box 20, Folder 153)
  - Desk file - Program Officer in Charge Lunch, 1986-1987 (Box 20, Folder 154)
  - East Africa trip, 1987-1988 (Box 20, Folder 155)
  - Edgar Beckham, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 156)
  - Desk file - National Service Task Force (Gordon Berlin - Urban Poverty Program), 1985-1986 (Box 21, Folder 157)
  - Desk file - K-12 students, 1987-1988 (Box 21, Folder 158)
  - Faculty early retirement, 1983 (Box 21, Folder 159)
  - Earl F. Cheit - Review of the European Management Education Program, undated (Box 21, Folder 160)
  - Work file - Rockefeller Foundation schools initiative, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 161)
  - Work file - Bialer Project (Enid Schoettle), 1990 (Box 21, Folder 162)
  - Affirmative Action Experience, Concerns, and Strategies in the Education and Culture Program, 1985 (Box 21, Folder 163)
  - Desk file - Math and science education program, 1988-1991 (Box 21, Folder 164)
  - Desk file - Social Sciences Initiatives for Undergraduate Education, 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 165)
  - Desk file - External Affirmative Action (Prue Brown), 1980-1986 (Box 21, Folder 166)
- Meeting and trip files, 1980-1991; 3; 2.57 Cubic Feet About 6.75 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Series consists of the meeting and trip files that Peter W. Stanley and the larger Ford Foundation Education and Culture Program created from between 1980 and 1991. Files regard internal meetings within the Education and Culture Program and between Education and Culture and other parts of the Foundation as well as meetings Stanley had with universities, foundations, and other institutions and individuals focused on issues and projects primarily related to higher education. Internal meetings chiefly concerned matters of program review and direction, while external meetings chiefly concerned projects and initiatives seeking or receiving support from the Education and Culture Program. Agendas, submitted papers, draft papers, program outlines, invitation and participant lists, and program outlines document the preparation of these various meetings and trips. There is also a lot of correspondence within the series that shows the follow-up communications Stanley had with the individuals and organizations he met and visited.
  - Barnes Collection at Lincoln University, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 167)
  - Soviet Union trip, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 168)
  - Ed Meade's Symposium, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 169)
  - Association of Fund Raising Officers (AFRO, Inc.) meeting and luncheon, 1989 (Box 21, Folder 170)
  - Quantitative Understanding: Amplifying Student Achievement and Reasoning (QUASAR) briefing, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 171)
  - San Francisco, California meetings, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 172)
  - Harare, Zimbabwe meeting and Mozambique, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 173)
  - Education and Culture Staff Meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 174)
  - Puerto Rico Community Foundation visit, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 175)
  - Education and Culture Staff Meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 176)
  - Washington D.C. trip - National Council of Less Commonly Taught Languages (NCLCTL), 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 177)
  - Berkeley, California/St. Louis, Missouri trip, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 178)
  - Hudson Mohawk Association Annual Awards Dinner, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 179)
  - University of Pittsburgh Learning Research and Development Center (LRDC)/Quantitative Understanding: Amplifying Student Achievement and Reasoning (QUASAR) Meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 180)
  - Education and Culture Staff Meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 181)
  - Trustees Meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 182)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1990 (Box 22, Folder 183)
  - Social Science Research Council (SSRC)/American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS) meeting regarding International Predissertation Fellowship, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 184)
  - Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education (WICHE) meeting, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 185)
  - The College Board meeting, Fort Worth, Texas, 1989-1990 (Box 22, Folder 186)
  - Roundtable Discussion: Curriculum Strategies to Improve Achievement in the Public Schools, 1988-1991 (Box 22, Folder 187)
  - University of California San Diego meeting - Faculty Advisory Committee on Upper Division Foreign Language Work in the Social Sciences, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 188)
  - Association of American Colleges Annual Meeting, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 189)
  - Education and Culture Staff/Budget Planning Meeting, 1991 (Box 22, Folder 190)
  - Mongolia President, Punsalmaagiyn Ochirbat meeting, 1986-1991 (Box 22, Folder 191)
  - Quantitative Understanding: Amplifying Student Achievement and Reasoning (QUASAR): Public Voice Project meeting - University of Pittsburgh, 1990-1991 (Box 23, Folder 192)
  - Yale University meeting, 1989-1991 (Box 23, Folder 193)
  - American Council of Teachers of Russian (ACTR) meeting, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 194)
  - University of California San Diego meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 23, Folder 195)
  - Harvard University meeting - Working Conference on Assessment, 1989-1991 (Box 23, Folder 196)
  - Transfer Assembly meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 23, Folder 197)
  - Harare, Zimbabwe meeting, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 198)
  - Desk file - Arts in liberal arts colleges meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 199)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) Program Review Meetings (personal notes), 1984 (Box 23, Folder 200)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP)/United States International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Reviews meetings, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 201)
  - Education and Culture staff retreat, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 202)
  - Desk file - Education and Culture/Developing Countries Program (DCP) Worldwide Meeting, Bali, Indonesia, 1984-1985 (Box 23, Folder 203)